<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Works on Vivid Theory</title>
    <link>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Works on Vivid Theory</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vividtheory.github.io/work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/VLT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/VLT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/VLT/lg/VLT_polefolder_canopy2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Vivid Light Tubes&#34; /&gt;
Underground parties, DJ nights, Nature Nocturne&amp;hellip; the vivid light tubes are becoming a familiar sight around some circles of the Ottawa nightlife scene.  The combination of programmable LEDs, a dazzling cover material, and unique programming produce some captivating effects.  Just check out some of these &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/user51003445/videos&#34;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/VLT/fullTest_small.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Vivid Light Tubes&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physically, the vivid light tubes are not complicated.  Strips of programmable LED are enclosed in cylinders of Rowlux illusion film.  This film has a pattern refractive index which creates a unique light diffusion effect.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/VLT/lg/VLT_repair.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;inside a Vivid Light Tube&#34; /&gt;
The individually addressable LEDs are driven by Fadecandy boards, which can be connected to different controllers (usually a laptop or raspberry pi&amp;hellip; depends on the application).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is standard practice for Vivid Theory, the light tubes are almost always controlled by custom software.  While there exist many excellent applications for controlling LED installations,  doing things from scratch has a unique appeal for theorists and coders. For live VJing (e.g. at DJ nights), the current incarnation of software is being developed in C++ using OpenFrameworks. This provides almost limitless possibilites for interaction and engagement with the art (sound reactivity, Xbox kinect, leapmotion&amp;hellip;).
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/VLT/DSC_0770.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Vivid light tube control&#34; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/impossible_illumination/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/impossible_illumination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exhibited at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://glowfairfestival.ca/&#34;&gt;2016 Ottawa Glowfair&lt;/a&gt;, Impossible Illumination is a physical implementation of the famous &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrose_triangle&#34;&gt;Penrose Triangle&lt;/a&gt; illusion.  If the segments have the same colour, the structure just looks like a plain triangle.  However, as the segments fade to different colours, it begins to look as though the three segments join at &amp;ldquo;impossible&amp;rdquo; 90 degree angles in 3D.  Unlike a 3D sculpture, here the illusion is created by colouring the different segments using programmable LEDs.  One might say that the physical structure is 2D, but the technology allows the illusion to extend into another dimension.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://vividtheory.github.io/img/installations/impossible_illumination/tent.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Impossible Illumination under a tent&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framing is created from stainless steel tracking, and LEDs are adhered to the frame boundaries.  The front/back faces are covered with a light-diffusing material to enable viewing from either direction. The use of steel tracking for the frame makes it light-weight and easy to transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LEDs are controlled by two Fadecandy boards connected to a laptop.  The LED patterns are rendered using a custom C++ application developed using OpenFrameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/impossibleillumination/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/impossibleillumination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/VLT/lg/VLT_polefolder_canopy2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Vivid Light Tubes&#34; /&gt;
Underground parties, DJ nights, Nature Nocturne&amp;hellip; the vivid light tubes are becoming a familiar sight around some circles of the Ottawa nightlife scene.  The combination of programmable LEDs, a dazzling cover material, and unique programming produce some captivating effects.  Just check out some of these &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/user51003445/videos&#34;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/VLT/fullTest_small.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Vivid Light Tubes&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physically, the vivid light tubes are not complicated.  Strips of programmable LED are enclosed in cylinders of Rowlux illusion film.  This film has a pattern refractive index which creates a unique light diffusion effect.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/VLT/lg/VLT_repair.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;inside a Vivid Light Tube&#34; /&gt;
The individually addressable LEDs are driven by Fadecandy boards, which can be connected to different controllers (usually a laptop or raspberry pi&amp;hellip; depends on the application).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is standard practice for Vivid Theory, the light tubes are almost always controlled by custom software.  While there exist many excellent applications for controlling LED installations,  doing things from scratch has a unique appeal for theorists and coders. For live VJing (e.g. at DJ nights), the current incarnation of software is being developed in C++ using OpenFrameworks. This provides almost limitless possibilites for interaction and engagement with the art (sound reactivity, Xbox kinect, leapmotion&amp;hellip;).
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/VLT/DSC_0770.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Vivid light tube control&#34; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/infinityofthree/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/infinityofthree/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exhibited at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grosselanterne.com/&#34;&gt;La Grosse Lanterne&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://upfest.ca/&#34;&gt;Upfest&lt;/a&gt; in 2015, this installation was a collaboration with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.provides.space&#34;&gt;Provides.&lt;/a&gt; collective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/infinityofthree/lg/infinityofthree_fulltest.png&#34; alt=&#34;Infinity of Three Test&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure is a 9x9 grid of mirrors, &lt;sup&gt;50&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; mirrors, and LED infinity mirrors.  The infinity mirrors are fascinating in their own right, but the entire structure is arranged
in an arc so that multiple reflections are generated as light reflects from different faces of the grid.  Think infinity mirrors inside an infinity mirror.  Moreover, the &lt;sup&gt;50&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; mirrors allow an outside observer to enjoy a kaleidoscopic
effect when standing outside of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each infinity mirror contains 60 individually addressable LEDs.  The LEDs are driven by a laptop via two Fadecandy breakout boards.  Pushbuttons on the centre console allow particpants to switch between different operational modes.  Some of the modes developd so far have included: preset patterns using GL shaders, sound reactivity, and live video capture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/infinityofthree/lg/infinityofthree_grosselanterne.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Infinity of Three at Grosse Lanterne&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One original idea was to use a camera to capture images from a plasma globe mounted on the console, and then
use these video frames to render patterns on the LEDs.  Unfortunately, it was discovered that the electromagnetic fields generated by the plasma globe caused excessive interference with the pushbuttons. A future design will improve the robustness to allow this unique mode of interactivity to be realized.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/soundcastle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vividtheory.github.io/work/soundcastle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sculpting sounds with your hands in the sand.&amp;rdquo;  Soundcastle was built for the 2016 Ottawa Maker Faire. It turned out to be quite a hit&amp;hellip; especially with kids.
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/soundcastle/lg/soundcastle_fullshot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sound Castle&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soundcastle is an augmented reality sandbox that is used to synthesize and play back sounds/music in real time.  This is a novel extension of an augmented reality project created by researchers in &lt;a href=&#34;http://idav.ucdavis.edu/~okreylos/ResDev/SARndbox/index.html&#34;&gt;Oliver Kreylos&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; group at UC Davis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soundcastle consists of a sandbox, an Xbox Kinect, and a projector. The Kinect measures the 3D surface profile of the sand, and the projector overlays a color-coded contour plot of the sand&amp;rsquo;s topography in real time.  This profile is then interpreted as an audio spectrogram, and used to generate an audio sample.  This audio sample is played back in real time for the sculptor to hear.
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/soundcastle/lg/soundCastle_sandClose.png&#34; alt=&#34;Soundcastle sand close-up&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spectrogram is a 3D plot used to visualize the frequency and amplitude content of audio. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vvr9AMWEU-c&#34;&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt; shows an excellent example of a spectrogram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Soundcastle, the projector displays a scroll line on the sand/contour plot to indicate the time position of the sound being synthesized.  This line moves across the sand at a constant rate and returns to the start after reaching the end.  In other words, Soundcastle is being used to create an audio loop.
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/soundcastle/lg/soundcastle_interaction1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Soundcastle interaction&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obligatory dog pic.
&lt;img src=&#34;img/installations/soundcastle/lg/soundcastle_dogpic.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Soundcastle with dog&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>